<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Religio jurisconsulti.</title>
            <author>Botrie, J.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 78 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77117</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3811</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1344_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209157</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868046</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868046</idno>
            <idno type="VID">169806</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77117)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 169806)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 177:E1344[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Religio jurisconsulti.</title>
                  <author>Botrie, J.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 26, 33-69, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Hood, and are to be sold at his shop in St. Dunstans Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: "J. Botrie".</note>
                  <note>Text is continuous despite pagination.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nou: 9".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>God --  Knowableness --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Claire Tolan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Claire Tolan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:169806:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>RELIGIO JVRISCONSVLTI.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Henry Hood,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in St. <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtans</hi> Church-yard. 1649.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:169806:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:169806:2"/>
            <head>To the Readers.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ell? Then it muſt to the Preſſe? yet Readers, yee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of many Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions and Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zes; my words therefore to you (though I am truely yours) are in generall, and but few, and thoſe not very pleaſing neither; (ſave onely that my Conſtitution compells mee to declare my Bow to Noble Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, to the truely knowing, wiſe, good man.) It is publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed out of pure Love and Pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty (in the true concernments)
<pb facs="tcp:169806:3"/>of Mankinde: And may it bee judged, <hi>Ex viſceribus cauſae;</hi> I am not therefore minded to begge any thing, claiming al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance of the neceſſary Inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents to a manly Action: I therefore wiſh every one of you (at leaſt) either ſo much true Wit or Honeſty, as will ſuſpend reproofe onely, till you will bee publick in it, my In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuity ſubſcribes, to refer to the generation of Wiſedome, who is the Foole or Knave in Print.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:169806:3"/>
            <head>DEO</head>
            <p>Maximo Optimo.</p>
            <p>Dicatur Conſecratur.</p>
            <p>Actio Perſona.</p>
            <p>For Right Advance of Vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</p>
            <p>For Certain Reſolve of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>For Effectuall moving the Will.</p>
            <p>For Due and conſtant Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:169806:4"/>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hoc ipſum eſt Coelo in terris frui: Quando mens humana in charitate move<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur; In providentia quieſcit, &amp; ſupra Polos veritatis circumfertur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Suave eſt in littore ſtanti Naves, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Suave ad Arcis feneſtram ſtanti, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sed nulla ſuavitas vel voluptas aequiparari potest huicipſi, nempe ut quis ſtet ſuper clivum excelſum veritatis, at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> inde errores, caligines, &amp; Tempeſtates in convalle ſubjacenti deſpiciat.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Mans minde is not a Paradiſe, unleſſe there be planted in it the full knowledge of good and evill.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <head>The Subject.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of the firſt Beings, Eſſence, Operations.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of the End in its externall Operations.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>How this End is to be performed, and of the ill finding and performing.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Where is the true Rule for performance, and the way for full Reſtauration.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:169806:4"/>
            <head>Religio Iuriſconſulti.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the firſt Beings, Eſsence, O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perations.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S every Beginning hath a cauſe thereof, for there is not any thing can give that to it ſelfe; ſo, <hi>In cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis non datur progreſſus in infinitum:</hi> We muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore come to a firſt cauſe; for among In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finity of cauſes, the True, the Prime is not, therefore <hi>in cauſa datur progreſſus in infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitum,</hi> to a Precedent eternity of Durati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and a Being there is, without Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, the which is incident to an Infinite Being, to which any thing, (conſiſtent with the abſolute Perfection) either in its Being, or in the manner thereof, cannot be denyed: and infinite this is in its Being;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:169806:5"/>For all Finites conjoyned cannot make up an Infinitie of Duration or otherwiſe: for that a finite thing ſhould be infinite, is a contradiction, as well as that an infinite thing ſhould bee finite. And alſo humane Reaſon being finite, and therefore its ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect comprehending any finite thing, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the cauſe thereof, muſt be infinite; as in its Operation and Adjunct, ſo in its Subject or Eſſence: this Being therefore is neceſſary and independant, Infinitie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Abſolute, and Preſent, without aide of poſſibilities or ſucceſſion, neither parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of motion and change, but hath an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall ſameneſſe in it ſelfe, and its neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Operations, aſ well to, as from eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie: The world therefore is not (as the Epicure firſt broached, and <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> and the Peripateticks held, contrarie to the former Votes of Philoſophers) neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie eternall (their lower Degrees, of Independent eternities, wherein there can bee none, are by themſelves ranked together with time) it being finite, and the finite parts to ſence, appearing to bee ſeverall and divided Beings, not made up all one, and the whole being (as it muſt bee) of a limited Operation,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:169806:5"/>neither hath it abſolute perfection; for whence proceeds the invention of Arts and Sciences, and our better performance of Actions? whence the diverſity of Enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties? ſubordinate and ſubſervient, (which alſo is not to be admitted among eternals, which are equall, and alſo among whom, there can be no end, or conſideration pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent, they alſo conſiſting of Contraries as appeares hereafter) one unto the other? And why was not the Prime Eſſence by them acknowledged, the author of all mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſource of all perfection, admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted (among their higheſt degrees of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities) to a Deity? Nor is the World ſo conſtant in any its properties and qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, as in its inconſtancy, alterations, variations and decay, neceſſarily conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent from the contrary matter, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of it conſiſts, its ſucceſſion helps not, as aforeſaid; and alſo where the cauſes and parts are temporall and meaſured, the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect &amp; the whole, cannot be of it ſelf eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall; and man ſure, if any, is to bee eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, he being the principall, and all other things for him, as appeares hereafter. But he is not, as of this world; for his temper, his minde, is here conſtant in inconſtancy,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:169806:6"/>unſatisfied, imperfect, and inthralled to the Lawes of Mortalitie; and though it be admitted, particulars reſolve into their Principles, and all things relieve nature in common, (which therefore needs it) yet thoſe Principles partake of no further Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing than before: And therefore <hi>Datur an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nihilatio,</hi> without an infinite power, (the contrary parts invading and abſolutely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring one the other, though where the ſubject is finite there bee no need thereof, as aforeſaid) as well as a higher being by Degrees, inſenſibly paſſeth to a lower: All things therefore in this world, being under Motion and Time, have a cauſe, which is either accidentall, or worketh by an intended due Operation; not acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, that is not eternall, as the firſt cauſe muſt be, as aforeſaid: Nor doth it give a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Being, but onely alters, and therefore rather helpes to deſtroy Being; and alſo the ſeverall parts of the World conſiſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of contraries in their particular Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and are of ſo high a faſhion, ſtored with ſuch manner of varieties, and ſo proportionable, and uſefull, in the totall, one unto another, that in <hi>Galens</hi> opinion, (who endeavoured otherwiſe) it was a
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:169806:6"/>ſoveraigne Wiſedome, a Perfectly Good, and Heavenly minde that cauſed it. The faſhion of man likewiſe is wonderfull, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven a miracle; and as he is the Lieutenant of the world, as appeares hereafter, ſo he is the abridgement of it, being capable to partake of every part thereof: All other things are alſo as fitly anſwering their proper Natures, and Degrees; And though Perfection in each kinde, be accruable by Degrees, yet never by meere accident, which onely produceth diſorder and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion; And then alſo the courſe of the World would not be ſo like it ſelfe, in its Operations, nor keep therein the Order and Harmony it now doth, and for all time hath done. All things therefore are cauſed by ſome intended due Operation, contrary to the hap-hazzard Opinion (which can extend onely to Accidents) (upon proportionable Alterations of the World; for the better Entities, the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Alterations, for the other, the leſſer; as by Moats of the Sunne, collected toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp;c. (a Production inconſiſtent, with a duration to eternity) received by the Epicures (from <hi>Democritus</hi> their Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) and other Accidentall Philoſophers.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:169806:7"/>This Cauſe or Being, (though with <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, Plotine,</hi> and others, it is farre more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent than Being, it giving it) is but one: for it being eternall, it is infinite, as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid; and therefore though it bee not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall, as appeares hereafter, yet it having no limits in its Being, and therefore having all Being in it ſelfe, no being can be conſiſtent with it, but muſt be of it. Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Perfection alſo conſiſts in Unity, and according to the Opinion of <hi>Proclus, Plotine</hi> and <hi>Zeno</hi> (the Patron of the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>icks) the denyall of its Unity, is therefore an abſolute denyall of its Being: The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall alſo of every thing is Unity; And of reaſonable Creatures which are to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the end of his Operations externall, as appeares hereafter, there is but one kinde, and all things in the world, though made up of contraries, tend onely to one Generall Being, without difference or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: And though two, and many Beings, are acknowledged by many Philoſophers, yet when they would be ſerious, moſt of them acknowledged onely One, Supream, the cauſe of all others. And the Poeticall Philoſophers, and <hi>Orpheus</hi> the firſt of them, which among their vaine imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:169806:7"/>firſt imagined ſeverall firſt Beings, when they were Reall, acknowledged onely One; yet it is poſſible, for this firſt Being, to make another Infinite Being, (contrary to <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> impoſſibilities) he being an Infinite Cauſe, and it not being a Contradiction. This firſt Being is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alſo Infinite (it being of an indiviſible ſingle Perfection, thereby the Infiniteneſſe of One excludes not the other) in all its Properties; and it is Spirituall becauſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall, and Simple, and Pure, (and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore fully capable of all things) <hi>compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> being latter to the things whereof compounded, and alſo containes varieties, which produce Motion and Change, is alſo Good and Perfect; for Vice and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection, are deviations from a true O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration, and departers from Eternity. It hath alſo in it ſelfe an Infinite Perfection of all things that have Being, or that any Being wants, or can imagine: For, <hi>Nil dat, quod non habet:</hi> This firſt Being is therefore a Pure Act, and therfore (though ever at reſt in it ſelfe) is alwayes neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily in Operation: And therefore (though Simple and One it ſelfe) hath Word, or Conception, and Operation, which is not
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:169806:8"/>a meere Reflexion of his Underſtanding, Minding and knowing himſelfe, (though that muſt be in his perfect Being, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, though all Underſtanding muſt be his Being, it being the Beginning of all Ends, as <hi>Plotine</hi> ſaith) as is generally conceived for an action of Reflexion, Onely, is not the full Operation of Reaſon and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, (which this Word and Concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion muſt be) neither are there therby pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced any externall Operations, they not being of the Eſſence of the firſt Being, as appeares hereafter: And alſo therefore upon externall Operations, another Word would then be ſubſtituted; the third Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er alſo, as appeares hereafter, would then alſo be made up of divers Beings or Poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities, which cannot be in Infinity, as aforeſaid. And though Word ſignifie Speech, yet therefore it doth not, as <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curius Treſmegiſtus</hi> uſeth it, ſtand for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall Speech onely; for that is not an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall ſubſiſtence, nor an eternall neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Operation of the firſt Cauſe. It is therefore the Internall Adaequate, neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and eternall Operation of the firſt cauſe, and therefore a Coeſſentiall, Coequal, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eternall Subſiſtence with it. This Word,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:169806:8"/>as it is the perfect adaequate Operation of his Underſtanding, hath been by Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, called the Wiſdome, and Maker of all things, as it, wherein all the treaſures of wiſedome are hid, but as begotten by him, ſo called, his Iſſue or Sonne: There is alſo in this firſt being, a Spirit or Power, proceeding from it, called by <hi>Mercury</hi> a Fiery God, which doth infinitely act up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the foreſaid Conception or Operation, otherwiſe, there were no contentment, yea a meer inſenſibility in the firſt excellent active Being; and alſo, external operations, would be without vigorous Livelineſſe and Effect. This Power was by Ancient Philoſophers, called perfect Love, and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall, in relation to the Eternall Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the internall word. This Spirit is alſo a ſubſiſtence, Coeſſentiall, Coequall, Coeternall with the firſt Cauſe, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall Word is for the reaſons aforeſaid, of the Word, and doth in Order, though not in Being, proceed from the firſt Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, through the Word, though not Begotten, as the Word is from the firſt Being. As there are theſe three (Power, Wiſedome, Goodneſſe) (rather Powers than Perſons, as moſt terme them) ſo
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:169806:9"/>there are no more; for all other Operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons muſt be externall, and paſſe emanant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out of the Agent: neither can theſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall be multiplied, they being neceſſary and proceeding from one, abſolutely ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle, and Indiviſible, even Unity it ſelfe, as aforeſaid: there are therefore no further Operations of Conſultation, and holding Parliaments by this perfect infinite Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, as many men expreſſe, whereby a fourth ſubſiſtence for the reaſons afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, of the Word and Spirit, would bee ſubſtituted, which is inconſiſtent with the Being, and infinite Perfection of this Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; This firſt Being as aforeſaid, cauſing all other Things, there is not any thing that hath an eternall Being with it, but muſt be from it: All other things therefore are produced as the <hi>Terminus, a Quo,</hi> (though not as the <hi>Materia ex Qua;</hi> whereupon the Philoſophers grounded an abſolute impoſſibilitie, and therefore not at all Feaſible, no not by an infinite cauſe) of nothing; the generall Vote of the later Philoſophers following <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> that they are eternall, becauſe <hi>ex nihilo nihil fit,</hi> is therefore erronious, and holds not (though between nothing and ſomething,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:169806:9"/>though not between ſomething and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, as appeares before, there be an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite diſtance) concerning the acts of an infinite Agent, with whom infinite things are as finite, and as feaſable, by a bare Ema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, without any Motion or Mutation, in any pre-exiſtent matter: And if there were a precedent Chaos, then this unlick'd confuſed Chaos ſhould be infinite and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, &amp;c. and then there would bee two Eternities, and the one ſhould have Power over the other, neither of which can bee, as aforeſaid. And why may not the matter be created, (as the <hi>Terminus a Quo</hi>) of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, as the former? according to the <hi>Platoniſts</hi> Tenent, the Forme being by their opinion the higher: And if there were Matter, there would be alſo Forme; for without it, (or deformity it ſelf, which then would be the Forme of it) there is no matter; and ſo againſt their opinion, by their opinion, a World is to be Eternall. But how can a Chaos? which hath nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Underſtanding nor Senſe, but is the comprehendable Object of them, contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to them, which are ſo farre above it? Do not the Philoſophers thereupon agree, that there are divers things in Nature,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:169806:10"/>which muſt have other kinde of Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning than from a Chaos? Doe not the conſtant defects and prevarications of all kindes, argue, that the matter deſires to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert to its Originall and <hi>Terminus a Quo,</hi> after its confuſion even to nothing? It is therefore proportionable to a higher Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, that it is made from nothing; for the diſproportion ariſeth onely from the not apprehending the power of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent: And ſo it is a truth above our Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but not againſt it: wee apprehend it not, it being above our Spheare, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of working. This Creation is made from the firſt cauſe, through the Word, by the Spirit, they being intirely coeſſentiall in Order aforeſaid, and is externall, and therefore not at all eſſentiall (they alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing temporary and meaſured) nor neceſſary in any kinde (as the <hi>Ariſtotelians</hi> would have it) either as an effect, or for the uſe, and behoof of the firſt Being, though the Word, Making it, be neceſſary. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore though this Eſſence bee a Pure Act, yet externall Operations may be deferred; And as the Philoſophers ſay, he was Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally in himſelfe, and therefore alſo might have done externall Operations, (as the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:169806:10"/>Creation of Spirits, &amp;c.) even from Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and therefore this world might bee from Eternity, though not eternall, by Creation. It is made by Word, there is no precedent Matter; and this Word muſt have an infinite Spirit, which by the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Philoſophers, is called, the externall Word. The Concluſion therefore is, that a moſt Excellent, Eternall, Infinite firſt Cauſe, neceſſarily begetting a Coeſſential, Coequall, Coeternall Word; from which neceſſarily proceeding a Coeſſentiall, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equall, Coeternall Spirit, through and by them hath Created all things Good, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to pleaſure. And though (as <hi>Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> ſaith) he is beſt expreſſed in ſilence, no Name or Deſcription being able to reach him by an infinite Diſtance; yet it being neceſſary to have ſome expreſſion whereby to Meane him, he ſhall be termed out of the Premiſes, <hi>Jehovah,</hi> and (with <hi>Plotine</hi>) deſcribed that He is, what He is: It is therefore evident, (though no Syllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſticall Demonſtration lyeth in the Caſe, it being a Cauſe) <hi>Per demonſtrationem in Orbem,</hi> That it is not Feare, or Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Nature, which Creates a God, (according to the Atheiſts Opinion)
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:169806:11"/>though it alſo proves a God, as appeares more hereafter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of its End, in its externall Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations.</head>
               <p>BY Negation, there might be more uttered, of this great <hi>Jehovah;</hi> but that being onely private, and it appearing that our Apprehenſions and Judgements are to attribute the higheſt unto him, a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative Manifeſtation ſhall not further bee inſiſted upon, but a further poſitive know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of him, comes not within the ſphear of Reaſon, it being a Created thing which cannot comprehend its maker, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Creatures below it are alſo but in part knowne, he being thereby diſcovered only <hi>ab effectu:</hi> and as the predicate is included in the nature of the Subject, and appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to us onely wonderfull, which is a weake broken knowledge, therefore alſo not fitly further to be enquired into; but as the Philoſopher <hi>Damaſcius</hi> ſaith, is to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:169806:11"/>be honoured in ſilence; our Apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons carrying no proportion to that Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and our judgements unable to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it; our imagination partakes onely of corporeall things, and is but a part of our ſenſitive faculty: And though our Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding is the higher part of us, yet we doe not underſtand but through the Senſes, though above them: (And ſo it may be ſaid, there is ſomething in the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, which never was in the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes;) And therefore I may juſtly judge that to bee which I cannot apprehend. My finite narrow Underſtanding, alſo muſt be aſtoniſhed and confounded, in further Inquiry in it; for finite cannot underſtand infinite: Settle I therefore my judgment, maugre the jealouſies of Apprehenſion (which not any Truth is Proofe to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand) yea, or the narrow confounded Conceits (which neceſſarily are in my underſtanding, as aforeſaid) which (not acknowledging <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> conceit, That alteration muſt conſequently bee in <hi>Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah,</hi> if the World bee not Eternall, it no more (yea not ſo much) altering him, than the Argument alters me) thinke it much forſooth, that there ſhould be an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:169806:12"/>Being ſo abſolute One, (though of neceſſity it muſt be ſo, as aforeſaid, being ſo ſolitary, as not to have, or admit any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, (the which denotes onely imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, to be relieved by another) yea ſuch a Being, which neither hath Beginning, or Capability of End (though they are meer Contradictions, as aforeſaid) yea they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come confounded, with their owne Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and Contradictions; That it ſhould bee of it ſelfe, yet altogether without it ſelfe, fix I my Poles, and <hi>Atlas,</hi> upon this certaine Truth, to guard this underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, non-pluſſed, not by due reaſon, which hath agreed unto mee, theſe very things; but by aſtoniſhment, being dazled by them, which is to be expected, as aforeſaid; and not look for more Light than noon-day, or ſuſpect an underſtanding and heart ſo much my owne, &amp;c. (The ſame things al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, muſt bee agreed, upon any ſuppoſition whatſoever: As if <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> would ſtate the world to be Eternall, &amp;c.) But though I am not capable of further knowledge of his Eſſence, yet it ought not to drive mee backward: But ſeeing all my good and happineſſe depends, and muſt be termina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted upon him, Inquire I of him, wherein
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:169806:12"/>he may, and is to be known, ſo farre as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to mans Duty, and is requiſite to Mans Good and Happineſſe; which muſt conſiſt in knowing and doing what hee hath appointed to be knowne and done, by man. Inquire I therefore, what he wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in his Creatures, which will bee ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered and concluded from his End in the Creation; and the Qualifications and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments of the Creatures, they being the Lawes whereby they are to worke, and behave themſelves: It is certaine, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very voluntary Operation, is done for ſome end; and the better the Operation is, the more proportionable, and determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned is the purpoſe of it: As the beſt Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration is from him, ſo the higheſt the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is able to performe, and moſt determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, muſt the end of it bee; honour and worſhip therefore, (man being fitted for it, as appears hereafter) (which is the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of Glory) is to be performed unto Him: And alſo a right mannagement, or behaviour among the Creatures (though that therefore cannot bee the ſole end of the Creation, as ſome conceive, every O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration being done for the Makers End, and not for the end of the thing made:)
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:169806:13"/>Good and Happineſſe therefore conſiſts in doing theſe, it being the true and full Operation of the Creature ſo made: And it muſt be done, becauſe determined. This end of his Operation terminates upon Man, and upon no Creature below him; for the Creature muſt be fitted, and have a proportion to that, for which it is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, (beſide the fitneſſe of the matter appointed) and thoſe that are fitted, and have a peculiar proportion, muſt be ſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, otherwiſe the Actions of <hi>Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah</hi> would be vaine: The other Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reall Creatures are not able to know any thing, of any Spirituall thing, as the firſt Eſſence is, as aforeſaid; or of honor &amp; wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip due unto him, as aforeſaid; or the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates of Reaſon, what is Good, or Bad, &amp;c. But keep only a ſenſuall ſingle courſe, being guided by the Rule of Senſe onely. But man, (duely qualified in his Reaſon, although hee differs not in any viſible Principle from Beaſts) pierceth into the Greateſt, and moſt Contrary Materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all things together, and is the better for it, makes univerſall Concluſions, and will not be confined by particulars, takes materiall things abſtractedly, and meerely in under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:169806:13"/>knowes alſo his owne materiall Being, and therefore he is more than any ſuch Being: Is able alſo to conceive of Vertue and Vice, Reaſon and Wiſedome, Folly and Madneſſe; which proceeds not from any Conſequence, or Excellency of Senſe (as ſome would have it) It being altogether of an abſtracted nature, is able (notwithſtanding his great Depravation, as hereafter appeares) to perceive, and judge of ſpirituall things, yea the great <hi>Jehovah,</hi> and that he is to be Honoured, and Worſhipped, and that by him, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid; hee is likewiſe appointed for E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity, although it cannot be proved, as many endeavour it, from the very Being of his Soul, (yet tell not what his Soule is, not any finite created thing, being able, to underſtand its utmoſt and higheſt grounds; for it gives the power to Underſtand and Judge) for that Contraries doe not purſue, but as they enſue one another, in underſtanding; and though deſtructive, each to other, maintain the minde, and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to, each from other; and for that the minde (as they ſuppoſe) is not liable, to outward or inward violence, in reſpect of the neare Conjunction of his mind and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:169806:14"/>body, and that ſo outwardly correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent with other Creatures, which there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their further blinde, and lame Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, from the eyes and legges, maimed, either in the Inſtrument, or ſenſitive Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, without prejudice to the underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, reach no more than my horſe: And in reſpect the Reaſons which ſhould prove it, to be Eternall in its very Being, muſt be from the ſoule it ſelfe, which is finite, and therefore cannot be eternall in it ſelfe, as aforeſaid; yet in reſpect of the Temper and operation of the minde, it will lively and indenyable appeare, that it hath pleaſed <hi>Jehovah</hi> to appoint him for Eternity: For man underſtands any ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall temporall Things, and is not ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with their fulneſſe, but they are empty and unſatisfactory unto him: There is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing great in this Materiall world to man, nothing in man to his ſoule, and therefore takes full delight and enjoyment in Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Eternall things; I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vaſt and unlimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Deſires and Operations of his minde, and is onely to be ſatisfied in the great <hi>Jehovah,</hi> who therefore is to bee the Eternall Object, of his Underſtanding; he is alſo able to underſtand Mortality, and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:169806:14"/>its difference from Immortality: So that when he argues for the former, he is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded by the latter; but the deſire attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to him, to continue his Memory by his Statues, Writings, &amp;c. and produced, in evidence for his Immortality, is but Temporary, and in reſpect of man, and many times a world is ſhort of it: Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can he have the Imaginary ability a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed unto him, to apprehend ſubſequent Eternity, though not precedent, he being finite. But whether he is ſenſible, that up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his diſſolution his ſoule dyeth not with him, and ſeekes for comfort in another place, ſeeing one muſt be dead firſt, before it can be determined, it muſt here be let a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone by me, till it ſhall bee determined, how it hath pleaſed <hi>Jehovah</hi> to appoint him for Eternity. Of which hereafter.</p>
               <p>Mans ſoule therefore, according to <hi>Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lens</hi> ſecond better opinion, is of a better being, than the perfecteſt materiall, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall Being, his Forme likewiſe is to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Heaven, and his Aſpect lookes to Eternity. And if he be not Eternall, why is he poſſeſſed with good or bad affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons concerning a ſucceeding Being? Are not Juſtice and Injuſtice meere fopperies,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:169806:15"/>and Vertue and Vice onely phantaſticall, if there bee not a ſucceeding time (and therefore Eternall, as appeares hereafter) for Rewards and Puniſhments, there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not any good without its bad, no Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue without its Allay here in this World, ſince Mans depravation, as appeares here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after? (So that humane actions receive their ſentence in this world, onely accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the exigences of Mutation, and that juſtly in <hi>Foro ſaeculi,</hi> it being fit and proper to the Condition and Temper of their Reall Being, the ſentence belonging to them upon their Internall, Eternall Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, onely is by <hi>Jehovah,</hi> to whom onely vengeance, and the abſolute univerſall Power, to ſentence belongs.) And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore exact Vertue and Goodneſſe is neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, and a certaine ſufferer in this World, and a Politick Vice the flouriſher, and the fortunate: And therefore alſo, why doe vitious Actions, though laid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the obſcureſt Mantle, and above all temporall controule bring Anxieties, (not to bee relieved, by any temporall thing (though through depravation and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of minde, there may be a ſlumber, and inſenſibility of them:) and therefore
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:169806:15"/>are not the puniſhments, as ſome would have them, they alſo not being, but as fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring puniſhments, which muſt be Eternall, as appeares hereafter) upon Man? and good delight to the Perfecteſt, the greateſt. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, if we conſider the Perfection of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hovah's</hi> Externall Operation, the Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the world; And alſo the Perfection of his Providence (which is of neceſſity upon his Being, and his Creatures depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, as aforeſaid, (contrary to the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Epicures) unlike it ſelf) (though it be (as it muſt be) granted, Mans beſt Fortune to conſiſt in the beſt things. If thou haſt goodneſſe and Knowledge, what if another partake of perfect Health? and Beauty? of Honours? or Pleaſures? Or the earthineſſe of Riches? Who would get by the Exchange? Theſe things are too low for <hi>Jehovah</hi> to give, or man to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive: And though it muſt bee granted, this Providence being according to his Being, muſt bee beyond our Apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, in ordering preſent Ills, to ſome great ſucceeding good) they will evidence that there is a further account to be made: The ſoule of man therefore, contrary to <hi>Pliny, Lucian, Lucretius, Epicurus,</hi> and others
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:169806:16"/>of that Habit, which onely judge Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>really, and Senſually, and confine them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the Operations of their ſenſitive Power, is appointed for Eternity; And their ſenſuall low conceits, not reaching Reaſon, which is the height, and true Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of man, ſhould no more prevaile with us, than their madde Opinions, as Atheiſts, as aforeſaid. Have not all People, Wiſe and Fooliſh, acknowledged a Deity? (of which the <hi>Scicilian Saturne, Cham</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Noah,</hi> was counted the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Vaine Superſtition is here a good Naturall Witneſſe for true Religion) to whom Honour and Worſhip was to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by them; and thereupon alſo, That Man is for Eternity, Religion, Providence, and Mans Immortality being inſeperable, as before, (beſide which nothing was ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall in the World, and therefore was not received into the eares by Tradition, but muſt be naturall, the Religions alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo different, of which hereafter.) Have not the moſt learned, and moſt perfect of man-kinde, perceived and rejoyced, even to Raviſhment in Immortality? Have not thoſe of the contrary Faction, been held generally vaine? Man is to take his Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:169806:16"/>from the Generall and moſt Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect: Error, Beaſtlineſſe, Inſenſibility may goe with others, and the Natures of moſt Creatures have ſway and powerfull Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations in particular men; can therefore ſuch a Concluſion be conſented unto, that Man is happy only when he is Beaſtly? It is not therefore a meer Fancy in man, that there is an Eternity for him, becauſe (as <hi>Pliny</hi> ſaith) he hath a minde ſwelled by Ambition to bee Immortall. Nor is it a vaine ſpeculation of a ſtrained apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or a Concluſion which hath been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived into the eares by man, and intoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated his Braines, and ſo exerciſeth a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious Tyranny over his minde: Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is there onely a meere capability in Man, to receive the Impreſſions of the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſall minde, (as the Sunne enlightens all eyes) wherein the variety ſhould a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe, either in reſpect of the diverſity of Actuall Imaginations, or Poſſible, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Conſtitutions, as <hi>Averrhoes,</hi> and <hi>Alexander Aphridiceus,</hi> flaſhingly imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; for then all men could not agree in ſome things, and then alſo, all of the ſame Conſtitution muſt in all; and therefore then, they two, could not ſo immediately
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:169806:17"/>have diſagreed about the manner of the varietie of Reception: Alſo, no man could then vary from his Imagination and Will; neither could he imagine any thing, but he muſt underſtand it: and alſo, there muſt then be a ſuddaine Perfection of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding and knowledge, without ſtudy and endeavour; Mans ſoule likewiſe by them is held to bee onely One, therefore the ſenſitive and vegetative Powers ariſe alſo from receiving the Impreſſions of the univerſall Minde. This ſoule is alſo, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, an Image of <hi>Jehovah,</hi> having a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance of Him, and Spirituall Things, as the Body hath of the World, and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall Things. There is therefore no <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thagorian</hi> Tranſmigration of Soules in the Literall Senſe, but onely as aforeſaid; this Tranſmigration being no ſatisfaction to Juſtice, as appeares hereafter; Nor any Puniſhment or Paine, but rather an Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, ſutable to a regenerate ſoule: And therefore the other Creatures, (yea the moſt loathſome, ſeemingly vaine, or refractory) being onely proper for the uſe and Powers of Man, are therefore, as <hi>Hermes</hi> ſaith, appointed for his uſe and ſervice. The Concluſion therefore, that
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:169806:17"/>
                  <hi>Jehovah</hi> created man, to Honour him in his Infinite Perfection, Power, Wiſdome, Goodneſſe, (as the lower Entities doe the other) to Worſhip him with Feare and Love, for giving him ſuch an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Being, with ſuch ſeverall Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts and Delights; And to demean them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves fitly among themſelves, and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the other Creatures.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How this End ſhould bee Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed: And of the ill Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and Performing.</head>
               <p>IT appearing that Man is to give Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Worſhip, even the fulneſſe of Glory to <hi>Jehovah,</hi> and alſo rightly demean himſelfe towards Man-kinde, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Creatures; It is neceſſary to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine wherein they conſiſt, and what is the full performance of them, which muſt appeare, upon taking a full conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Premiſes, concerning <hi>Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah,</hi> and alſo a true Examination, of the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:169806:18"/>Qualifications of Man, they being the Laws whereby he is to behave himſelf, as aforeſaid, what therfore is proportionable and fit for us to do, Directly or Relatively, as the Rule for our performances. But ſtay, we are, and always have been, deeply taxed with Prevarication; and that we are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled of thoſe proportionable Endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments wherewith we were fitted, that we are now become full of Inconſtancy, Weakneſſe, Vanity, Vice, that our Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are meerely Complexionall, and that we will adhere to them, more than to the cleareſt cloſeſt Truths; And that wee will ſacrifice our ſelves in this our madneſſe to any lawleſſe Opinions; and ſuch our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate and diſorderly frenzineſſe, it is therefore neceſſary for us to examine our ſelves: For till we have rightly diſpoſed, or ballanced, or fadomed our ſelves, our Apprehenſions, Judgements, Wills, and Affections, muſt be, not onely as wee are diſtempered, but alſo lead us amiſſe. It ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares before, that Originally wee were Right, and being created by <hi>Jehovah,</hi> for thoſe ends aforeſaid, we had therefore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility ſo to continue, without any Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or diſpoſition to the contrary: Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:169806:18"/>therefore is the opinion, which concludes a neceſſity of mans pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varication, in that hee conſiſts of Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, which warring civilly among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, muſt procure it. Be it agreed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude man now fallen; As <hi>Jehovah</hi> crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Man good and perfect, from nothing, ſo he created him to continue ſo, from no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, as aforeſaid: It is not therefore ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that man ſhould fall, though it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares of neceſſity that he is fallen, which will be made alſo apparant, in each parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, by ſifting the endowments of man particularly. It appeares before, we were made to give full Honour and Worſhip to <hi>Jehovah, &amp;c.</hi> But are we not now ſcarce able to acknowledge him, whom wee ought to Honour and Worſhip? And un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to conceive the Honour and Worſhip which is to be done unto him, (of both which more hereafter:) Neither have we any free conſtant diſpoſition, and motion to performe it. Our mindes alſo are grown fully and wholly ill and vitious, and are as infectious one unto another, as a Plague<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in one body is to another: Our minds delight in madneſſe, and it is a pleaſant thing ſometimes to be fooliſh, and there is not any vanity which will not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce;
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:169806:19"/>our ſenſitive Power hath now the chiefe Rule of us, and even devoured our Underſtanding, and we runne Riot, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing violently, wilfully, and without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of Underſtanding and Knowledge, of Goodneſſe, or the Honour and Worſhip due to <hi>Jehovah,</hi> which are ſhaken off as unjuſt Tyrannies, tranſported to our Fancies and Luſts: Yea, our Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding hath alſo made a League too with it, is become a mighty inventer of Miſchiefes, and proſecutes them with Ignominious Induſtry, whereby wee are become a Torment to our ſelves and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Doe we not chiefely inſlave our ſelves, to ſenſuall, momentany, earthly things, and care not for Goodneſſe, Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of Underſtanding, and thoſe Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable things, which properly belong to us? But as <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſaith, We are farre worſe than Beaſts, which keepe their courſes and meaſures: Where is that charitable Affection? that ſociable, ſutable beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour? that ſimple eaven cleareneſſe, which is due to our fellow Creatures? Sure it conſiſts not in Savage Gripings, Extortions, or Fawnings; in Simulations, and Profeſſions of Vertue and Goodnes, thereby to gaine advantage to our ſelves:
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:169806:19"/>and ſetting the ſtampe of Vertue and Goodneſſe onely upon that which condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth to our owne Ends: Nay, there is no exact Vertue and Goodneſſe to be found, no Mundane Graces without their ſpots, (it not conſiſting in covering or avoiding Vice, or doing good, for ſomething elſe;) no Good without its Bad: And therefore as it is uſeleſſe and unprofitable here, ſo alſo it is not ſafe (I meane a Noble and univerſall Vertue, and Goodneſſe, not a ſevere Habit, for particular Occaſions, which is the higheſt Vice habiting her ſelfe with, and ſeating her ſelfe in the place of Vertue) but is of neceſſity, to be Artificiall, and receives its eſtimate accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to its Condition here, from the Proportion it carryes, with the Exigencies of Mutations: What need our Morall In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, our Lawes and Governments, (which were impertinent, but that we are Fooles and Knaves) if we are not out of Order? But how ſhould this come to paſſe? Certainly man could not ſet him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to worke out his owne Ruine; nor could he take Pet againſt <hi>Jehovah,</hi> or have a minde averſe from ſerving him; neither would <hi>Iehovah</hi> carry any hard
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:169806:20"/>hand over him: It muſt bee therefore ſome Pride, or ſuch aſpiring, overweening carriage, as <hi>Plotine, Mercury,</hi> and <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roclius</hi> ſay, that muſt procure this diſabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: Upon which over-weening, aſpiring carriage, muſt follow of all; not to its true height and ſoveraigne goodneſſe, but to Vanity and Darkneſſe, below it ſelfe, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to Senſuality; Vertue and Goodneſſe being wounded, and annihilated by rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Vice: And Vertue and Goodneſſe dying, Man cannot but dye to Goodneſſe. Which hath been of long long continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, even beyond all humane Antiquity, (yet muſt ariſe from One, from whom all have deſcended, all being ſo alike defiled, and ariſeth not from any Conſtellation, or Imitation) and for ought as appeares yet, it may be from Eternity, it appearing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the World, may bee from Eternity: However <hi>Iehovah</hi> is Eternall, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Man is an infinite Tranſgreſſor; And ſo hath with all his Pudder, reduced him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to a infinite worſe condition than juſt nothing: Conſider wee but the Vanities, Vices, Hobgoblins, of one dayes Words, and Actions, what ſay we when we ſhall have ſuch a Collection of our whole lives?
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:169806:20"/>When we ſhall ſee ſuch Forreſts of Wilde Beaſts, and ſuch Sources of Errors and Vices? and yet wee are not Senſible of theſe Truths; and therefore we are Ill to Death, and our Malady is Mortall, or rather Immortall: It appearing Man is an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Tranſgreſſor, and that there is an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity for man to come, wherein are Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards and Puniſhments; and therefore Puniſhments being our due, wee muſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect an Eternity in Puniſhment. What courſe ſhall wee take to bee freed from this overwhelming Miſery? Can an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Excellent Being be brought to enter into a Reconciliation with a meere Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall, an unjuſt nothing, which hath entred into a Rebellion againſt his Soveraigne Good, for meere Vanity? Thereby de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying the end of his determined Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, as aforeſaid: What if there bee Perfection of Heroick Vertue in him, kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping him from Revenge, and taking occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to torment Man; but making him, ſlight, yea pitty him? Yet it appeares he is neceſſarily juſt, and cannot admit Vice to goe unpunished: What if man humbled himſelfe, for that the Treſpaſſe was by Pride? yet was not juſtice ſatisfied, and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:169806:21"/>right adminiſtred, though there be there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Infiniteneſſe of Heroicke Vertue in him, and Humility enough in us: yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Opinion of <hi>Hierocles,</hi> (becauſe ſure he could goe no further) man, unleſſe he make ſatisfaction to Juſtice, cannot be diſcharged: And how can Man that is finite, ſuppoſe he were not vitious in all his Actions, ſatisfie for his Offence Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, as aforeſaid? Onely, by ſuffering an Infinite time, that, which he being fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, cannot ſuffer in time; therefore hee cannot be relieved for that ſatisfaction to Juſtice muſt bee given by that very kinde which hath offended. Well therefore may the <hi>Platoniſts</hi> confeſſe, That they know not how it may be done; yet it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares, that one mans ſatisfaction, will ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie Juſtice for all: for it is not a meere perſonall fault in man, as the Philoſophers hold, but is in the Nature of man, it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming by one mans fault, as aforeſaid; and therefore exact Juſtice is ſatisfied by one mans ſuffering: But it appeares before, as impoſſible for man to give ſatisfaction, as for a finite thing to make an infinite: There can therefore bee no meanes for Mans Reliefe, but from <hi>Jehovah</hi> himſelfe,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:169806:21"/>even miraculouſly; And therefore mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles muſt be done to make it knowne un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us. And hath not this Excellent Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite <hi>Jehovah,</hi> to Actuate his Goodneſſe and Wiſedome, ordayned ſome way, whereby Man may be diſcharged? Is hee not Infinitely mercifull, and as much Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy as Juſtice? and doth it lye ſuſpended, though it be a pure Act, as aforeſaid: And ſeeing many have found out their preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rication, and diſabilitie, and endeavoured to have avoided it, as aforeſaid; Hath not Mercy ſtrove with Juſtice for a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation? Are not all men abſolutely in this caſe? And doth not <hi>Jehovah</hi> deſire, even Will, that there be a performance of the End of his Externall Operations, and that there ſhould be a joyfull parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Eternity for man (and a Repara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Ruine introduced by the Fall of Lucifer and his Angels, as ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive) as at firſt was allotted? Sure it is not in the ſtrength, much leſs in the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of man, and in his poſſible imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, to hinder him: And ſure there is ſome way of accommodation, otherwiſe Juſtice would long agoe have ſeized upon many, even temporally here. Alſo <hi>Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah</hi>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:169806:22"/>is as Infinitely mercifull, beyond our Conceivings, as his Being is, as aforeſaid. Let it be carefully conſidered therefore in our enſuing Diſcourſe, if any ſuch action can bee diſcovered, and then ſticke wee there, when we are well; and there muſt we finde the Excellent, Infinite <hi>Iehovah,</hi> as aforeſaid; And it will be an undenyable Argument, That wee are in the ready way to performe the end of his Externall Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations. Therefore alſo the true examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Indowments, and Operations of man, muſt be tranſacted, with a minde Strong, Faire and ſound, and duely tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered, freed from all Selfe-love, Intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rancies, Vanities of Imagination, and Anxieties; Goodneſſe and Simplicity muſt poſſeſſe the heart: Then let a clear, bright, high underſtanding, advanced and regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated by Arts and Experience, take the ſtrict Dictates of our owne mindes; then ſoare abroad and take a view, of the Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues and Goodneſſe of old time, (and of all times) and let their Actions where they are Good and Vertuous, be a Proofe even Demonſtrative unto us, they being neare the Truth; for though the knowledge of the Creatures, and things produced by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:169806:22"/>receive Advance and Perfection in time, yet ingrafted Principles cannot, they being not capable of Addition; and alſo they being neare an Obliteration, through our Prevarication, as aforeſaid: Obſerve wee therefore, what the ſtrong, Good, unſuſpected Sages, and Fathers have left unto us; And that no Errors, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Deviations may defile us, let not any Cuſtome of manner of Education, Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Ipſe dixit, virtus ſpecifica contra ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantem Principia;</hi> no ornament of Speech, no Extravagant or ſpecious Pretences, or Actions, exerciſe any Tyranny up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our duely enfranchiſed minde, or put a Cheat upon us, with Errour to boot. The Concluſion therefore is, That man could have known, and done, the end for which he was made; but that he is totally preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricated, unable to ſatisfie Offences paſt, to know or doe for the time to come, and muſt uſe his beſt meanes to looke out for his Cure and remedy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:169806:23"/>
               <head>Where is the true Rule for Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance; And the way for full Reſtauration.</head>
               <p>IT appearing that herein muſt bee ſet downe the true Rule for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of <hi>Iehovah's</hi> End in its Externall Operations, which muſt bee done as we would have Good and Happineſſe, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyd Infelicity: As alſo that here muſt be diſcovered our Cure and Remedy, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by wee may bee relieved againſt our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame Diſabilities and enſuing miſerie, as aforeſaid; Uſe therefore is to be made of our moſt Impartial, trueſt examinations, and exacteſt diligence; wee being utterly and Eternally wretched, if it be miſtaken. This Rule of Performance, (uſually cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Religion, as the Tye or Bond upon the Creature to performe the Duties belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to the Creator) is but one, in Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; for <hi>Iehovah</hi> is but one, to whom it is to be performed; and all men are ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:169806:23"/>in the ſame Condition, as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid. This Religion requires onely ſuch Performances, as are Proportionable for Man to know and doe to <hi>Jehovah;</hi> and as are agreeable to the Powers and Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications of Man, as aforeſaid: wherein though there are Generall and Grievous Diſabilities; yet mans minde duely diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, hath Ability to diſcerne and judge rightly, as before; For though it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares, Man loſt his good Qualifications, yet not his Reaſon and Underſtanding, we alſo continuing men as before: and it appearing alſo hereafter, that <hi>Jehovah</hi> hath appointed a way for mans Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Reſtauration. Let us therefore examine our Religion by them; and in thoſe things for Knowledge or Action, which conſiſt in Quality, as Goodneſſe, Badneſſe, Vertue, Vice, either Poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, or in Degrees, Let us therefore imbrace them, though they are thwarting, or above our preſent Tempers and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. Therefore wee cannot miſſe the Truth, for that either there hath been, or will be, ſome right Service and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip performed unto <hi>Iehovah,</hi> it being the end of his externall Operations, as
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:169806:24"/>aforeſaid, whereof he cannot bee diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed or hindred. Examine wee there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Religions of the World, Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning before the foure firſt Monarchies, (which cannot be very farre from the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy of the World; for then was the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of Sciences, there being alſo not many People, or any Record or Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriall extant of further time, but onely that there had beene a generall Deluge of the World: yet all Sciences could not thereby be quite deſtroyed and forgotten, ſeeing ſome of Man-kinde did and muſt remaine, neither their Memorialls total<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſtroyed; for their Letters were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graved in Tables of Lead, &amp;c. And ſure there was but this one generall Deluge, for the Reaſons given before: And alſo, ſure we ſhould have had ſome notice of them, as of this and other Particular Deluges.) <hi>Hermes,</hi> ſaith one, the true God, made man; Man made gods; and into theſe Images, Fiends, Evill Spirits, partly voluntarily, partly by the Art Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicke of Man, entred into them, and were worſhipped by men; and that <hi>Mercurie</hi> ſhi Grandfather at that time was wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hispped as one of the greateſt gods, hee
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:169806:24"/>having ſet up his Statue, and by Art Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicke, brought a Fiend into it. Thus was Religion, except the Religion declared by <hi>Moſes,</hi> who lived in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> which Religion is the moſt Ancient, that is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded or remembred; of this Religion, (our end and ſtay is there) hereafter. In the Monarchies among the Aſſyrians, there were ſo many gods, as Townes, among the <hi>Perſians,</hi> as Starres, among the <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians,</hi> as Fancies, among the <hi>Romans,</hi> as were in the World (and more too) except onely the true God, as appeares hereafter; which was not there admitted, though allowed ſome reſpect by them, in the Countrey of the Jewes, becauſe (as <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cero</hi> ſaith) That God beſeemed not the Majeſty of their Empire (<hi>Anabis</hi> and <hi>Pryapus</hi> did.) It is true, the great <hi>Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah</hi> became not that Majeſty of their Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, which was not only as High but A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove their Worſhipfull gods, which were created by it, whoſe Temples were their Tombes: The Devotions done unto them, Old Wives Tales, Their Originals, Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Lifes, Deaths, Pedigrees, may be eaſily ſet downe: for <hi>Varro</hi> hath been ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry carefull of his gods, leſt (as hee ſaith)
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:169806:25"/>they might partake of ſo great a misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune as to be loſt. Sure it is impoſſible, that ſo learned, ſo gallant a Man ſhould bee ſo ſenſeleſſe, ſo mad <hi>Quoad hoc;</hi> ſo that it is to be thought, he feared men (as well hee might do) more than thoſe his gods. Well then might this bee a time to make men gods; their flattering Minions making them by their Images and Idolls meere I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deots; yea the moſt vitious, unhewen, and Beaſtlieſt men (for none elſe ſure would be) ſought to be, and were made gods forſooth. We will not meddle more to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen our Predeceſſors Nakedneſſe, than to perceive the truth of things; onely the honeſt Tooth-Drawer, god <hi>Eſculapius,</hi> (no leſſe I promiſe you) becauſe the half-headed <hi>Iulian</hi> forſooke <hi>Iehovah</hi> for him, (wherein this our Diſcourſe renders him more Knave than Foole) becauſe hee had not ſo good a mind to ſerve <hi>Iehovah</hi> as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> did, it being but of latter time we cannot ſo eaſily paſſe over; <hi>Iulian</hi> hath been at the paines, in Honour of him, to draw this wonderfull gods Pedigree from <hi>Iupiter;</hi> and deſcending by the Sun, ſtiled him Child of Heaven: but ſeeing no leſſe Pdi gree will ſerve his turne, under Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:169806:25"/>I ſhall ſtile him this once. Childe of the Earth: for he was (as a man may ſay) A Baſtard, be it by <hi>Apollo's</hi> Prieſtes, or <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollo</hi> himſelfe, (it matters not whether) by faire <hi>Corinis:</hi> Poore <hi>Iulian</hi> thou art a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle miſtaken; For <hi>Coronis</hi> was but one of the lower Forme, <hi>Venus</hi> at moſt. What though theſe Gods (that would be reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled by Images, mans workmanſhip, and thoſe none of the beſt neither, but ugly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>favoured Images (like themſelves) where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they were as wiſe as their Worſhipers, who may very well goe together) have done things beſide the ordinary courſe of man, (it is very hard if their Fiend, their Devill, or their God-head could not doe ſomething extraordinary) As their <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus Pocus Legerdemaine</hi> Miracles, which were not done, but to their Favourable, Gentle Spectators, who at moſt, had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther truſt than try. And their Prophecy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, (the wiſeſt whereof thoſe at <hi>Delphos</hi> were uſually infuſed into young Wenches by their Privy parts) which were alwayes in generalties and and incertainties, and ordinarily in the untruths too; and were done onely by Naturall Cauſes, <hi>Apollo</hi> divers times complaining, that hee could
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:169806:26"/>not reſolve things moved unto him, the Poſition of the Starres being divers from his Obſervation and Rules. And it is ſaid, that Man is capable to doe any ſuch Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, yea any Action that a Fiend can doe; Mans ſoule is an Image and Reſemblance of ſpirituall things as the body of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall things, as aforeſaid: And theſe Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were done by vitious Agents, their Actions being vitious, diſhonourable to <hi>Ichovah,</hi> and Man-kinde alſo. The Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices done to theſe gods were not onely Vitious, but Cruell and ſenſeleſſe, men Offring their Children, and themſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them: Actions that proceed not from the Qualifications of Man, as aforeſaid: And all the myſteries of their Service were but Schooles of Villany: yea theſe Gods themſelves being more capacious, and partaking of a greater Latitude of Evill, commanded even the greateſt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vills to be done, over and above their Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Service, as a ſatisfaction due unto them. Alſo as <hi>Cicero</hi> obſerves; Why was there not a courſe taken concerning the Inward Motions of the Minde? Or a puniſhment for them? Nay there was no Prohibition or Puniſhment, but ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:169806:26"/>Inſtructions, and directeſt meanes were made uſe of by theſe gods them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, for the utmoſt Advance of all Vice and Brutiſhneſſe, and for the making of Men, Devills indeed, like themſelves. The inward evills, the evill of the heart, is knowne onely by <hi>Iehovah,</hi> the true God, who made the minde, and knowes it; and with which hee is chiefely to bee ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured and worſhipped, as before: Is there here any ſatisfaction to juſtice for mans offences, which muſt bee in the true Religion, as aforeſaid? Can it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in the Barbarous killing of Men and Children? which can bee no other than Heaps of Villany, and Blaſphemies againſt <hi>Iehovah,</hi> or in Offring to him the Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſence of Vice? an Offring for the devill. It is too evident theſe kindes of gods reach not our former Concluſions, and there are too many of them to bee good: Vanity therefore, and beaſtly Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Idolatry was and is in a great part of the World, which (to ſatisfie onely their Follies, not medling further with their vices) under a Tyrannicall, Ignoble, Scoundrell Superſtition, even to the ſhame and abaſhment of Man-kinde, make finite
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:169806:27"/>weake Beings, fooliſh madde Opinions, and Conceits, yea meare Phantaſmes a Deity, their God; Though if we ſhould pieke and chuſe, ſome of their Gods were Men, ſome of them as Gods, and ſome as Devills among men, yet dependant and Mortall, not Gods of Men. The ſayings of ſome of their wiſe men, which would ſpeake out a little, nay of a whole Nation, that they were not clean ſottiſh, to account ſuch things gods, but onely allowed them a ſuperiority for ſome excellency in them, (Although it is true, Civill Reſpect was onely in the Beginning thereof; but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards being diſguiſed in Hiſtory be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came changed) cleareth them not of it; For thoſe that they accounted of for Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill Government, or State-Merit, or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious villany, were by them worſhipped, as Demy Inferior Gods: Thoſe which found out or performed, and perfected, ſome materiall Thing, for the ſuſtenance or well Being of Man, had the higheſt Worſhip, as to the greateſt gods, done un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them; <hi>Scavola</hi> a High Prieſt among the <hi>Romans</hi> ranked his Gods into Poetical, Philoſophicall, and Politicall, whereof ſome of them were not at all to be known
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:169806:27"/>by the People. Having had enough of theſe gods, Come wee now (diſcarding all Thought or Memory of them) to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Religion, which is ancienteſt, and was received in <hi>Paleſtine, Canaan,</hi> or <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea,</hi> by the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> or <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> which obtained the Province of <hi>Syria</hi> to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; with whom alone from the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the world the Knowledge and Worſhip of the true God, and the firſt forme of ſpeech continued, and is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in a Book uſually called the Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, not deſtroyed, or corrupted, or altered, in the many ſad Deſolations of that Kingdome, or the Ruines of any time; that in the Front containes; <hi>In the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning God Created, &amp;c.</hi> And in all points as there manifeſtly appeares runnes pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallell both in Relation to the Creator, or Creatures, either in themſelves, or in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation one unto the other, either directly or conſequently, with our former conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions: And therefore it is the true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; And therefore, and for the Reaſons hereafter wee muſt agree with all thoſe which have received it, That the Booke called the Old Teſtament, was compiled by the ſpeciall Ordination and Aſſiſtance
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:169806:28"/>of <hi>Iehovah</hi> in man, notwithſtanding the Objections, That it appearing Man hath the proportion in him as aforeſaid; And alſo for that the Iſraelites had expreſſe rules by Tradition, to relieve their diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities, contracted by Mans Prevaricati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for they would not have received and undergone many things, therein contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, as upon the Opinion and Will of a Man; And for that the great <hi>Iehovah,</hi> would ſure have done it by ſome higher courſe, whereby it would have appeared clearely and manifeſtly to have been done by him; Therefore it may bee done by man onely, who is too ready to doe miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous Actions, and to fall into Error, to which Suſpition and Doubt it is liable. But this cannot bee the ſole Act of man without Gods ſpeciall Ordination and Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance: For man here truely, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes Declares the vices and weakneſſes of himſelfe, and all his, chargeth and condemneth himſelfe and them fully, and throughly; affects not Reputation or Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, or any thing, but neglects and waves Honour, Eaſe, and any other thing, and willingly undergoes, chuſeth, glories and delighteth in miſery, even death it ſelfe
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:169806:28"/>that he may performe <hi>Iehovah's</hi> Honour and Worſhip, and declare the good and right way, though there was no formall humour thereof, then in faſhion. And though merit and Praiſe were worthily allowed there by other Authors, which were no great Friends; And can theſe things ſo neare and deare to man, bee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes waved by him, without any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation or alteration? No more zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous or loud, not more frequent in fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding out uſefull Directions, where Profit, Honour, Popularity, or ſome other Intereſt is concerned, or ſome glimmering thereof may be perceived, than where it concerns <hi>Iehovab's</hi> Honor and Worſhip, and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and Truth, with the loſſe of them; ſo that <hi>Iehovah's</hi> right Honour and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, bare Goodneſſe, and naked Truth, are the full Deſigne, and onely End: And in Order whereunto all of man is fully and wholly waved, and laid aſide. It is alſo concerning matters Eternall and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite, and many other things, not conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents, or derived from Nature, out Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comitant. And (notwithſtanding it was made not long from the Infancy of the World, when it was but in an unfurniſhed condition, as aforeſaid) is in the whole fit
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:169806:29"/>and proper, and altogether free from vice and errour, (although its ſubject matter be various, above the apprehenſion or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of man) and in ſome parts exceeding full and ſignificant, (as the containing all vertue and goodneſſe in ten Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements (the which are abridged in two Sentences, <hi>Love God with all thy heart, thy Neighbour as thy ſelfe.</hi>) Its ſeverall Propheſies (being the maine part there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of) made by ſeverall Perſons at ſeverall Times, ſo farre diſtant from themſelves, or their accompliſhment, ſo particular, certaine, of ſuch concordance, and ſo fully accompliſhed though not at all depending upon Naturall Cauſes, or to be foretold by them, (which onely hold a meane betwixt Neceſſity and Chance) although they were fully and exactly knowne, demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate it to have been done by the Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Iehovah;</hi> The Prophets were likewiſe men ſtricken in yeares; ſo that though it could bee proved, whereas <hi>Fruſtra fit Potentia que non reducitur in Actum,</hi> That Prophecying is a power Naturall (or Artificiall, or Daemoniacall, or what they will) as Conceiving is for the preſent, and Memory for things paſt,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:169806:29"/>yet they muſt have ſuch want of Heat, and defect of Imagination, that they could not thereby ſo truely performe it; for it is agreed, thoſe muſt bee intended, even to deſtraction, if it be not rationally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded from true Principles. Alſo man of ſo much Senſe and Honour, could not be ſo Foole-hardy, upon his owne credit, and his bare word, ſo poſitively, and majeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally, without Grounds of Reaſon, and Principles maintaining his Concluſions, to have juſtified his diſcourſe, (which though the Philoſophers therefore ſlighted, though it bee an Argument againſt them, it being alſo concerning Principles and Grounds of Being which ought not, not cannot come within the virge of Proof by Principles, but only be declared) although there were no written, Foot-ſteps before, and have charged the obſervance therof, even in things of higheſt Concernment equally upon all. Hee by whom it was done, muſt either be a wiſe good man, or a fooliſh and bad man: If he were wiſe and good, how dared he to Arrogate ſo much to himſelfe, even many times the Perſon of <hi>Iehovah</hi> himſelfe? And how could he doe ſuch an Act to befoole Man kinde,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:169806:30"/>where there is no Advantage to himſelfe? If he were fooliſh or bad, how could he doe a good thing ſo exactly? be ſo fully for <hi>Jehovah's</hi> Honour and Worſhip, and Mans Welfare? be ſo throughly for ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and goodneſſe? and trace ſo exactly the wayes of Truth, the Birth of upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? For though the verieſt Devill many times will ſeeme an Angell of Light, yet it is meerely an affected Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, under a faire viſage, to make an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, not to bee ſtable there, but dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving on to ſome Concluſion Deſtructive. And although man had ſuch a Proportion as aforeſaid, yet it appeares how grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſly he is diſabled, ſo that man in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, nay the greater part, nay the exacteſt of men, cannot attaine to a due know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, nor diſcover a meanes for their diſcharge and repaire; as appeares by the confuſed rambling erroneous Opinions of the able Philoſophers, who though they vented many things concerning our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Truths, yet in Truth, they miſſed, (neither can there be gathered from them ſcarce good Problemes) they being mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſo much foppery and vanity; And to attaine ſo farre, they alſo were
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:169806:30"/>either <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> or came into <hi>Aegypt</hi> for Inſtruction, or received <hi>Moſes</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples by Tradition, (though they ſlighted them, becauſe there was no Probation of them, yet gave their approbation to them) and generally the farther in ſituation of Region, or ſucceſſion of time, they were from <hi>Moſes,</hi> the more phantaſtically, vain and erroneous. That which a wiſe man knoweth alſo, he delivers not ſo certainly, and poſſitively; nor hath it ſufficient ſtedfaſtneſſe, for as <hi>Richelieu</hi> joynes them, Reaſon is contradicting, Nature is corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; That alſo which procured the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Admiration, in the Certainty and Beauty of Truths, which procures the greateſt Delight, is ſubject to fall off. And <hi>Porphiry,</hi> one of the exacteſt Knowers, notwithſtanding his great knowledge, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tooke himſelfe (as to the ſurer ſide for the Preſent) to the Faction of the ſecond School of the Epicures. And although the Iſraelites had expreſſe Rules by Tradition, (yet not concerning moſt things contained in this Scripture, neither was the Scripture compiled (except in ſome main things) til Tradition was ſilent: Good and gracious therfore was <hi>Iehovah</hi> in giving us our duty
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:169806:31"/>Writing, for if we were not able to know the generall and plaine parts of it, how ſhould wee every particular and higher Action? <hi>Iehovah,</hi> before it was written, had tryed all other meanes with us; for when our vices and errors, had in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner blotted out the Law, firſt imprinted on our Natures, then was there, through a due Conſtitution of Minde, a Tradition, as Sir <hi>Walter Rawleigh</hi> hath it, of this Law: It was then the next courſe, unleſſe hee had left man in his blindneſſe, for <hi>Iehovah</hi> to take, when man became ſo corrupted, that his Law was choaked and razed out of Man, and Tradition alſo, (except in ſome few principall things) ceaſed. This fully ſatisfies the other Cavill, for that <hi>Iehovah</hi> did not in ſome higher courſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt it and ſet it off with a greater clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, it being concerning ingrafted Principles, and a Law imprinted upon the Heart; and the next way to Tradition, which was next to that imprinting of it on mans heart, and therefore certaine and ſufficient to man. It followes therefore, notwithſtanding the Cavills, That it was made up of the pickings and chuſings of the vanities of former time, (they being
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:169806:31"/>ſo like, I trowe, as appeares before) and that it is a Remnant of the Religion of the former Times, (which is true onely, as before, and no more, than as the Truth is before the Fable,) And that it was the more exact, becauſe the Jewes, were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in Aſtronomy and Magick, (than which nothing is there more forbidden, nor any thing made more uſe of, by the falſe gods, &amp;c.) That, that which is du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contained in the Old-Teſtament, is done, by a ſpeciall power, and Ordination, of <hi>Iehovah;</hi> It being alſo cleare by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Hiſtories of Nations, (which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine many things, over and above what is therein contained, though they were no Friends to the Jewes) the matters of Fact (being the works of a God) to bee true, And that it was not compiled at one time, and ſo cunningly made up, each part to anſwer the whole, but directly that it was made in Succeſſion of Time, and at thoſe times either of which the Inditors write; or thoſe they particularly mention. And though the Jewes were but few, (One true Underſtanding is better, than a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thouſand, Counterfeit or Deficient, it not being there, as in Burdens where
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:169806:32"/>through many, helpe may be contributed: And we are to follow one cleare-ſighted, before a blinde or darke World) and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt in greateſt and conſtant Afflictions (Temporall things bee neither fit for <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hovah</hi> to give, or Man to receive) yet thereby every man, became a Preacher for the True God; and as <hi>Seneca</hi> obſerves of that Nation, That they being overcome alwayes prevailed, and though vanqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, (by what meanes he knowes not) overcame their Conquerors, and gave Lawes and Religion unto them; For ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Conquerors acknowledged, the Jewes God and his Worſhip to bee the true: yea, no ſerious Heathen man ever abſolutely denyed it: But the Jewes ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver would acknowledge any other, And rather ſuffered all miſeries than forſooke it. Therefore alſo notwithſtanding this Direction or Rule from <hi>Iehovah,</hi> contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the forward Conceits of Ignorant, Narrow mindes, Man muſt be prepared with thoſe things which are required to make him of a true Underſtanding and Judgement, For its chiefe purpoſe is for the redreſſe and Direction of Qualities and Manners, as aforeſaid; as alſo for the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:169806:32"/>Inabling our underſtandings, where the Beſt preſent ſtate of our Naturall Abilities are deficient; It being alſo ſubject to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Senſes and Conſtructions, as other things are, and requiring our Prudence and Underſtanding. Looke we therefore conſtantly into that perfect Rule, which therefore will ſhew unto us our ugly De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formities, whether outward or inward (a Diſcovery fit onely for the true God, as aforeſaid.) And therefore this Scripture will be a Schoole-Maſter to ſhew us, and to drive us to looke for our proper Cure and Remedy, without which wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine ſtill utterly loſt, as aforeſaid; And without ſuch a Cure and Remedy revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in it to what purpoſe? Unles to breed Deſparation, which produceth violent fearefull effects, which would be but Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty and Vanity? Should a Rule or Scripture bee diſcovered to vitious Man? And alſo in ſeeking for a Cure and Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, we muſt look onely towards <hi>Jehovah,</hi> as aforeſaid: And in it we finde, that up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Examination of the Originall ſinne, there was a Saviour declared: and it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares there, That he ſhould bee the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Word the Sonne of God, who ſhould
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:169806:33"/>take upon him the Seed of man, become fleſh, and ſuffer for mans ſinne; there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one Truth in Scripture: and Reaſon; is not here according to our former Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions, Man to ſuffer for the Offence, God to overcome? and by reaſon of the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion contracted with mans Nature, to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer alſo thereby to make up a full infinite Satisfaction, even as Infinite as <hi>Iehovah</hi> himſelfe, as it muſt bee, as aforeſaid; But as it is not therefore requiſite to Juſtice, ſo it is impoſſible, according to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits of ſome, That this Word, or Son of God ſhould ſuffer in his very Eſſence, it being the ſame with <hi>Iehovah</hi> himſelfe, as aforeſaid. Alſo, though it were neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, in reſpect of Union with the Divine Nature, that it ſhould be pure, that was to ſuffer; yet it was not neceſſary to Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, as is conceived, for a ſufficient Infinite ſatisfaction by Mans Nature muſt diſcharge Man kinde to exact Juſtice, as aforeſaid. Let us therefore ſee if this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction be performed, although it bee not neceſſary, as ſome have weakly Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined, That this ſhould be performed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there is any Benefit to bee received thereby, for a certaine, though after per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:169806:33"/>of what is due to Juſtice is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, eſpecially to <hi>Jehovah,</hi> to whom, all Time and Things, are as Actually and Really, as they are in themſelves preſent. In this Old Teſtament we finde it onely declared, not performed: for although in many parts of it, it ſpeaks a preſent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance; But that is onely in determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and benefit of it, at that preſent time to them: Seeke wee therefore if we can finde ſince any performance of it; for it is neceſſary that it bee ſometimes done. In a Booke called the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or Goſpell, We finde there was a full punctuall performance; This Booke running alſo parallel with our former con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions, partaking likewiſe of the Senſe of thoſe Reaſons, which concluded us, that the old Teſtament was by the ſpeciall Power and Ordination of <hi>Iehovah</hi> in man; wee muſt agree that this is ſo alſo, and that the Saviour therein mentioned, is the right Saviour. But in this our ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall Diſcourſe, wee neither meddle with Jewes nor Turkes, which admit the Old Teſtament, (and eſpecially the Jews) the Controverſies chiefely depending up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:169806:34"/>Scripture Contents, and therefore is not proper to bee decided in this place. Theſe two Teſtaments therefore laying downe and declaring what man is to know or doe to or concerning <hi>Iehovah,</hi> and Declaring the Meanes for mans full Reſtauration, hath therein all, that man is to know, or doe; and Declares <hi>Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah's</hi> will fully. Here is the true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, it declaring a true God, a right Service, and a ſufficient Saviour for Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde: To what purpoſe ſerve the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans and Infidells Barbarous Sacrifices, in Offering men Infinite onely in Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences? The Jewes Lambe, a vaine and ſmoaky ſavour? <hi>Mahomets</hi> Prayers, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries and Treaſons againſt <hi>Iehovah?</hi> The Beginnings onely and no other, (as <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phery</hi> ſaith) being able for it. And muſt we not now, in wonder, and raviſhing Aſtoniſhment adore the Infinite good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Wiſedome, and Power of <hi>Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah</hi> our Creator and Recreator? Was not the Act of our Redemption, the Act of Wiſedome, the ſecond Being in the Trinity: And are not Goodneſſe and Power Infinitely appearing in it? Wee
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:169806:34"/>are therefore Bound, and Bound againe to make good our ſecond Concluſion, with our Mouthes and Hearts, and to kindle our benummed Abilities to a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant zealous endeavour of Obedience, making <hi>Jehovah</hi> our onely end, Hee beeing the Aiming Point, for our Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding and Judgement, the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect welfare for our Will, and the ſole continuing reſting Point to the whole man, and farre more, in the Fruition, and Actuall partaking of, then in the Deſire, or Speculation, which is his ſole Felicity, which muſt bee above that it makes happy: caſting away Riches, as Earthly things, conſiſting onely in Fancy, and Opinion, and mighty pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curers of Vice, uncertaine, and not fit to be deſired for themſelves: Voluptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe as Senſuality, ſoone partaking of Turmoiles and diſcontents, Unleſſe that of the Underſtanding, which is the higheſt Pleaſure, and muſt terminate on <hi>Iehovah,</hi> as aforeſaid, Honours, as Blaſts of men, and Shadowes of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things, even Vanity, a Multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of many Miſchiefes for nothing,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:169806:35"/>And Policy which meddles onely with the Vaine Things of this world, and and hath ſuch a Tincture and Mixture of Vice and Miſchiefe, (Wee ſpeake not of true Wiſedome (which alſo is onely a cure to make Man-kinde it ſelfe) the deareſt Gift in Nature, borne to relieve Humane Imbecility, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve Humane Society) that it is meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Brutiſh. Settle wee our ſelves there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſtable upon our True Intereſt, as aforeſaid, All other things being either Vitious and Brutiſh, or Froth and Smoak, againſt all Cavills of Imagination, with a firme Reſolution, Maugre our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempered Natures, which admit, not onely our Habituall Complexionall O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, but alſo our Suſpitions and Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayes, to oppoſe and beare downe in our Mindes fully proved Truth: So our Reaſon, ſhall make us ſtedfaſt, and our Beliefe, ſure.</p>
               <p>Let this ſuffice for our Rationall Diſcourſe, upon theſe Subjects; This Concluſion being, That the Bookes of the OLD and NEVV TESTAMENT, Commonly called the Scriptures, are
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:169806:35"/>the True and Perfect Rule for the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of JEHOVAH'S Honour and Worſhip, And that they Declare a Right Way and Meanes for Mans full Reſtaura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Sic Cogitavit</hi> J. BOTRIE.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Fol.</hi> 1. <hi>line</hi> 14. with the abſolute, <hi>read,</hi> with abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute. <hi>f.</hi> 7. <hi>l.</hi> 5. for impoſſibilities <hi>r.</hi> impoſſibility) <hi>f.</hi> 9. <hi>l.</hi> 21. Word is for. <hi>r.</hi> Word, for. <hi>f.</hi> 11. <hi>l.</hi> 15. the former? <hi>r.</hi> the forme? <hi>f.</hi> 13. <hi>l.</hi> 25. a Cauſe) <hi>r.</hi> a Cauſes.) <hi>f.</hi> 14. <hi>l.</hi> 7. private, <hi>r.</hi> privative. <hi>f.</hi> 16. <hi>l.</hi> 2. aforeſaid being, <hi>r.</hi> aforeſaid) being. <hi>f.</hi> 19. grounds, <hi>r.</hi> ground. <hi>f.</hi> 21. <hi>l.</hi> 8. is <hi>r.</hi> to. <hi>f.</hi> 25. <hi>l.</hi> 24. <hi>Aphridy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceus, r. Aphrodyceus. f.</hi> 26. <hi>l.</hi> 22. regenerate, <hi>r.</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate: &amp; <hi>l.</hi> 28. therefore that, <hi>r.</hi> therefore is, that. <hi>f.</hi> 34. <hi>l.</hi> 5. as <hi>r.</hi> is: &amp; <hi>l.</hi> 17. frenzines, <hi>r.</hi> Frenzies. <hi>f.</hi> 35. <hi>l.</hi> 29. which wil, <hi>r.</hi> which it wil. <hi>f.</hi> 36. <hi>l.</hi> 27 Extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, <hi>r.</hi> and Extortions. <hi>f.</hi> 38. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> 6. of all, <hi>r.</hi> a fall. <hi>f.</hi> 41.28. Many, <hi>r.</hi> Man. <hi>f.</hi> 43. <hi>l.</hi> 10. of <hi>r.</hi> or. <hi>f.</hi> 44. <hi>l.</hi> 6. its <hi>r.</hi> his. <hi>f.</hi> 46. <hi>l.</hi> 27. ſhi Grandfather, <hi>r.</hi> his Grandfather.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
